<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="tutorialbm5">
  <title>Tutorial Using SCEC Benchmark 5</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>
      This tutorial walks the user through the steps necessary to
      construct, run, and view the results of a benchmark problem
      (SCEC Bemchmark 5). This problem examines the viscoelatic
      (Maxwell) relaxation of stress from a single, finite, dip-slip
      earthquake in 3-D without body forces. 
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect2>
    <title>Problem Description</title>
    <para>
      The model domain is 24 km by 24 km by 24 km (0 km <= x <= 24 km;
      0 km >= y <= 24 km; -24 km <= z <= 0). The model domain is
      composed to two materials. One material occupies the top-half of
      the domain -12 km <= z <= 0km while the other occupies the lower
      half, -24km <= z < 12 km. Both materials are Poisson solids with
      Lame's constants (mu and lambda) equal to 30 GPa with Maxwell
      viscoelastic properties. The top layer has a viscosity of
      10^{25} Pa-s (and is essentially elastic) while the bottom layer
      has a viscosity of 10^{18} Pa-s.
    </para>
    <para>
      The reverse fault dips at an angle 45 degrees. The top of the
      fault sits at x = 4 km with the bottom of the fault at x =
      20km. The fault surface is confined to the region 0 km <= y <=
      16 km and -16 km <= z <= 0 km. The slip distribution is 1.0 m of
      uniform thrust motion for -12 km <= z with a linear taper to 0
      at z =- 16 km.
    </para>
    <para>
      The boundary conditions on the lateral and bottom edges of the
      mesh are the displacements from the analytical elastic
      solution. These displacements are held fixed through time.
    </para>

    <para>
      INSERT FIGURE HERE
    </para>

  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>Prerequisites</title>
    <para>
      You should have already installed PyLith-0.8. In this tutorial
      we assume that you are using NetGen
      (http://www.hpfem.jku.at/netgen/) to generate the mesh and
      ParaView (http://www.paraview.org) to view simulation
      results. You may use other packages, but some adaption (not
      covered here) will be necessary.
    </para>

  <sect1>
    <title>Stage 1: Download</title>
    <para>
    </para>

    <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
      <listitem>
	<para>
          Download the tutorial tarball
          (http://www.geodynamics.org:8080/cig/Members/willic3/pylithusers/lithomopinstallation/downloads/unworked_benchmarks.tar.gz)
          and unpack it in a location of your choosing. You may also
          wish to download the worked example tarball
          (http://www.geodynamics.org:8080/cig/Members/willic3/pylithusers/lithomopinstallation/downloads/worked_benchmarks.tar.gz)
          to compare your results or start at an intermediate
step. 
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
          Once you have unpacked the tarball, you will have an
          "unworked_benchmarks" directory.  Go to the "utils"
          sub-directory and edit the makefile as appropriate (it is
          presently setup for g77). You will need to make the
          following executables in order to generate the inputs files
          for PyLith-0.8 from NetGen output.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Stage 2: Setup</title>
    <para>
    </para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
