<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<preface>
  <title>Preface</title>

  <!-- SECTION +++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
  <section>
    <title>About This Document</title>
    <para>
      This document is organized into three parts. Part I consists
      of traditional book front matter, including this preface. Part
      II begins with an introduction to PyLith and proceeds to the
      details of implementation. Part III provides appendices and
      references.
    </para>
  </section>

  <!-- SECTION +++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
  <section>
    <title>Who Will Use This Documentation</title>
    <para>
      This documentation is aimed at scientists who prefer to use
      prepackaged and specialized analysis tools. Users are likely
      to be experienced computational earth scientists and have
      familiarity with basic scripting, software installation, and
      programming; but are not likely to be professional
      programmers. Of those, there are likely to be two classes of
      users: those who run models and those who modify the source
      code.
    </para>
  </section>

  <!-- SECTION +++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
  <section>
    <title>Citation</title>
    <para>
      The Computational Infrastructure for Geodynamics (CIG) is
      making this source code available to you at no cost in hopes
      that the software will enhance your research in geophysics. A
      number of individuals have contributed a significant portion
      of their careers toward the development of this software. It
      is essential that you recognize these individuals in the
      normal scientific practice by citing the appropriate peer
      reviewed papers and making appropriate acknowledgements in
      talks and publications. Citation information ...
    </para>
  </section>

  <!-- SECTION +++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
  <section>
    <title>Support</title>
    <para>
      Current PyLith development is supported by the Southern
      California Earthquake Center, the National Science Foundation,
      and the CIG. Current EqSim development is supported by
      internal U.S. Geological Survey funding. Pyre development is
      funded by the <ulink
      url="http://www.doe.gov/engine/content.do">Department of
      Energy's</ulink> Advanced Simulation and Computing program and
      the <ulink url="http://www.nsf.gov/">National Science
      Foundation's</ulink> Information Technology Research (ITR)
      program.
    </para>
  </section>

  <!-- SECTION +++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
  <section>
    <title>Request for Comments</title>
    <para>
      Your suggestions and corrections can only improve this
      documentation. Please report any errors, inaccuracies, bugs,
      or typos to cassie (at) geodynamics.org.
    </para>
  </section>

</preface>
